莫札特
Mozart!
莫札特，原谅我的罪行
Mozart!Forgive your assassin!
我承认是我害死你的
I confess, I kiIIed you!
我杀了你，莫札特，原谅我
Si, I kiIIed you, Mozart.
慈悲...莫札特，原谅杀你的人
Mozart, pietu! Forgive your assassin!
原谅我，莫札特
Forgive me, Mozart!
萨列里先生，快开门，乖一点
Signore Salieri,open the door, be good now!
先生，我们为你准备特别的
Signore, we have something speciaI for you.
这是你一定会喜欢的
Something you're going to Iove.
好好吃
Is that good!
相信我，这是我一辈子吃过最好吃的东西
Signore, beIieve me...
...this is the most delicious thing I ever ate in my Iife!
你不知道你错过了什么
ReaIIy, you don't know
what you're miss--
别闹了，先生，快开门
AII right, that's enough!
Open the door.
先生，如果你不开门
我们会吃光所有的甜点
Signore, if you don't
open this door...
...we're gonna Ieave nothing
for you.
我们什么都不留给你
而且我也不来看你了
And I'm never gonna come
see you again!
彼德雪佛原著改编
阿玛迪斯
莫瑞亚伯拉罕
汤姆赫斯
伊莉莎白贝里吉
原著小说与编剧：彼德雪佛
制片：索尔沙恩兹
导演：米洛斯福曼
早安，神父
Good morning, Father.
萨列里先生
Herr Salieri?.
不要理我
Leave me aIone.
我不能不去理受到折磨的灵魂
I cannot Ieave aIone a souI in pain.
你知道我是谁吗
这没什么差别
Do you know who I am?
That makes no difference.
在上帝的眼中
众生都是平等的
AII men are equaI in God's eyes.
是吗
向我忏悔吧
Are they?
Offer me your confession.
我可以让上帝宽恕你
I can offer you God's forgiveness.
你对音乐的了解有多深
How weII are you trained in music?
一些，我年轻时学过
是在哪里学的
I know a IittIe.
I studied it in my youth.
就在维也纳
-Where?
-Here in Vienna.
那你一定听过这首
Then you must know this.
我好像没有听过
I can't say that I do.
这是什么
What is it?
当时是非常受欢迎的歌曲
这是我写的
It was a very popuIar tune in its day.
I wrote it.
那这一首呢
Here, how about this?
我们第一次演奏时
这首获得满堂贺彩
This one brought down the house
when we pIayed it.
怎么样
WeII?
对不起，这首也不是很熟悉
I regret it is not too famiIiar.
你没听过我任何一首歌曲吗
Can you recaII no meIody of mine?
我原来是
全欧洲最有名的作曲家
I was the most famous composer
in Europe.
我一个人写了40出歌剧
I wrote 40 operas aIone.
Here!
这一首怎么样
What about this one?
这首我听过
Yes, I know that!
真是太棒了
That's charming!
对不起，我不知道这是你写的
I'm sorry, I didn't know
you wrote that.
这一首不是我写的
I didn't.
这是莫札特的
That was Mozart.
伍尔夫阿玛迪斯莫札特
WoIfgang...
...Amadeus Mozart.
你就是你责怪自己谋杀的人
The man you accuse yourseIf
of kiIIing.
你听说了
You've heard that?
这是事实吗
Is it true?
看在老天的份上
For God's sake, my son...
如果你有忏悔的需要
...if you have something to confess,
do it now.
现在忏悔吧，让自己能够心安
Give yourseIf some peace.
他是我的偶像
He...
...was my idoI.
莫札特
Mozart.
他的名字
随时随地都在我心中响起
I can't think of a time
when I didn't know his name.
我在玩游戏的时候
I was playing games...
他就在帮帝王，国王
罗马的教宗演奏
... when he was playing music
for kings and emperors.
Even the pope in Rome.
我承认，我嫉妒
I admit, I was jealous...
人们告诉我有关他的传闻
... when I heard the tules
they told about him.
人们不是说这个神童
而是教导他一切的父亲
Not of the brilliant prodigy...
...but of his father,
who had tuught him everything.
我的父亲根本不在乎音乐
My father, he did not care for music.
当我告诉他
我多么希望能像莫札特一样
When I toId him...
...how I wished I couId be
Iike Mozart...
他会说，你为什么
想当马戏团的猴子
...he would say, ''Why? Do you want
to be a trained monkey?
你希望我把你当成马戏团怪物
去全欧洲表演特技吗
You'd like me to drag you around,
doing tricks like a circus freak?''
我要如何告诉他
音乐对我有多重要
How couId I teII him...
...what music meant to me?
我父亲诚心向上帝祷告
While my father
prayed earnestly to God...
希望能够生意兴隆时
我会偷偷的祷告
...to protect commerce...
...I would offer up...
...secretly...
那是一个小男孩
最骄傲的祷告词
...the proudest prayer
a boy could think of.
上帝，使我成为伟大的作曲家
''Lord, make me a great composer.
让我透过音乐赞美您的荣耀
Let me celebrate your glory
through music...
让我自己也能因此得到荣耀
...and be celebrated myself.
亲爱的上帝，使我闻名全世界
使我永垂不朽
Make me famous through the world.
Make me immortal.
我身亡之后
让所有的人赞美我的音乐
After I die...
...Iet peopIe speak my name
with Iove for what I wrote.
为了回报
我愿意献出我的贞洁
In return...
...I wiII give you my chastity...
我的努力，我的谦卑
我每一刻的生命
...my industry...
...my deepest humiIity,
every hour of my Iife.
阿门
Amen. ''
你知道后来怎么了吗
奇迹发生了
And do you know what happened?
A miraclel
法兰西斯...
我的人生永远改变了
My Iife changed forever.
我知道这全是上帝的安排
这是很明显的
I knew God had arranged it aII.
That was obvious.
一下子我是个
小镇里沮丧的男孩
一下子我就来到了维也纳
那是属于音乐家的城市
One minute I was a frustrated boy...
...in an obscure IittIe town.
The next I was here...
...in Vienna, city of musicians...
约瑟夫帝王，音乐之王
...and Emperor Joseph,
the musical king.
在几年之内
我就成了他的御用作曲家
In a few years, I was his court
composer.
是不是很不可思议
Isn't that incredible?
几年来我每晚坐在
奥地利皇帝的身旁
Every night I sat with
the emperor of Austria...
与他一起二重奏
教导陛下读乐谱
...playing duets with him...
...correcting the royal sight-reading.
事实上他根本没有任何听力
ActuaIIy, the man had no ear at aII.
那有什么关系
他热爱我的音乐
But what did it matter?
He adored my music.
告诉我，如果你是我的话
你敢以上帝之名发誓吗
TeII me....
If you had been me...
...wouIdn't you have thought
God had accepted your vow?
相信我，我是坐怀不乱
美色诱惑不了我的
And beIieve me, I honored it.
I was a modeI of virtue.
I kept my hands off women.
我日以继夜地教音乐
很多人我都免费教授
I worked hours every day
teaching students, many for free!
帮助那些无助的穷困音乐家
无穷无尽地工作
Sitting on endIess committees
to heIp poor musicians.
Work, that was aII my Iife.
感觉真的是很棒
And it was wonderfuI.
大家都喜欢我
Everybody Iiked me.
我也喜欢我自己
I Iiked myseIf.
直到他出现
UntiI he came.
他来到维也纳
演奏自己的音乐
He came to Vienna to pIay
some of his music...
他当时是沙兹堡主教的门客
...at the residence
of the prince archbishop of SaIzburg.
我立刻去那里找他
Eagerly, I went there to seek him out.
那一个晚上
改变了我的一生
That night...
...changed my life.
我穿过宴客厅的时候
开始与自己玩游戏
As I wandered through the salon...
...I played a little game with myself.
这个男人在4岁的时候
创作了第一首协奏曲
This man had written
his first concerto at the age of 4...
在7岁的时候
又写出第一首交响乐
...his first symphony at 7,
12岁时就创作第一出歌剧
a full-scale opera at 1 2l
这种才华是不是
会很明显地写在脸上呢
Did it show?
Is tulent like that...
... written on the face?
他到底是哪一位仁兄呢
Which one of them...
...could he be?
找不到莫札特
Mozart is not here.
别闹了
没闹...
-Stop it!
-I am.
-I am stopping it.
我没有闹...
I am! I'm stopping it. SIowIy.
慢慢的，看到了没有
我停下来了
There. You see? I've stopped.
现在我们又要开始了
不要...
-Now we're going back.
-No!
你不知道你身在何处
这里一切都是本末倒置的
Yes! You don't know where you are.
Here, everything goes backwards.
人们倒着走
倒着跳舞，倒着唱歌
PeopIe waIk and dance and sing
甚至倒着说话
and even taIk backwards.
这真的是太愚蠢了
为什么，人们倒着放屁
-That's stupid.
-Why? PeopIe fart backwards.
你说，我生病了
Say I'm sick!
是的，你是病的很严重
Yes, you are. You are very sick.
不，倒过来说
No! Say it backwards, shitwit!
重严很的病
音同亲我屁股
Saa-I'm-sick....
Sick, kiss.
I'm, my. Saa....
Kiss my ass.
你再说...
我不要玩
Eem-iram!
-I'm not pIaying!
-Say it, it's serious.
快说，这是很严肃的
说，我给嫁
It's very serious.
嫁...嫁给我
Iram....
Marry me.
我才不要嫁给你呢
你是个魔鬼
I'm not gonna marry you.
You're a fiend.
你爱我是可
Ooy-voI-I-tub....
可...是...我...爱...你...
Tub...
...but I....
Love....
But I Iove you?
便大的我吃
什么
-Tish I'm tee.
-What?
便大的我吃
-Tish I'm tee.
吃我的大便...
-Eat.
-I'm, my.
-My.
Tish. Eat my shit.
你这只肮脏的猪
You fiIthy fiend!
你这个肮脏...
You fiIthy--
我的音乐
My music.
他们没有我就开始了
They've started without me.
那就是莫札特
That was Mozart!
那个嬉笑怒骂
心中充满邪恶的怪物
That giggIing, dirty creature
刚刚还在地板上爬着
I'd just seen crawIing on the fIoor.
我认为演奏会进行的很顺利
没错
-I think that went weII, don't you?
-Indeed.
维也纳人
就是会欣赏优美的音乐
The Viennese know good music,
don't you think?
你不认为吗
当然
CertainIy.
阁下
Your Grace.
莫札特
Ah, Mozart.
为什么
-Why?
阁下，什么为什么
-Why what, sir?
为什么我要在我的宾客面前
受仆人的羞辱
Why must I be humiIiated
in front of my guests...
...by one of my own servants?
你真的是太得寸进尺了
The more Iicense I aIIow you,
the more you take.
如果阁下对我不满意
可以让我走
If His Grace is not satisfied,
he can dismiss me.
我要你立刻回去沙兹堡
I wish you to return immediateIy
to SaIzburg.
你父亲在那里
很有耐心的等着你
-Your father is waiting for you there.
-No, Your Grace!
不，阁下，我宁可你让我走
很明显的我没做好
I wouId prefer you dismissed me.
It's obvious I don't satisfy.
我不打算让你走
I have no intention of dismissing you.
You wiII remain in my service...
你仍然要当我的仆人
但是要多学些行为规范
...and Iearn your pIace.
在纸张上看起来平凡无奇
On the page it looked....
Nothingl
一开始很简单
几乎有点可笑
The beginning simpIe, aImost comic.
低音管，低音号
好像生锈的铁盒子一样
Just a puIse.
Bassoons, basset horns...
...Iike a rusty squeezebox.
然后突然出现了高音
And then, suddenIy...
...high above it...
单一的双簧管
...an oboe.
一个音符不变的飘浮着
A singIe note, hanging there,
unwavering.
直到被黑管取代
UntiI...
...a cIarinet took it over...
变成了如此悦耳的音乐
...sweetened it into a phrase
of such deIight.
这可不是马戏团猴子
所写出来的乐曲
This was no composition
by a performing monkey.
这是我前所未听的音乐
This was a music I had never heard.
充满了如此的情感
无法满足的欲求
FiIIed with such Ionging,
such unfuIfiIIabIe Ionging.
我似乎是听到了上帝的声音
It seemed to me I was hearing
the voice of God.
失陪
Excuse me.
上帝为什么要选择
这愚蠢的孩子做为她的工具
But why?
Why would God choose an obscene child
to be his instrument?
我想不可讳言的
这一定是个意外事件
It was not to be beIieved.
This piece had to be an accident.
It had to be.
最好是这样
It better be.
莫札特有多厉害
How good is he, this Mozart?
他非常杰出，陛下
He's remarkabIe, Majesty.
上个月我听过
他相当杰出的歌剧
I heard an
extraordinary opera of his Iast month.
叫做“克里特王”的歌剧
-Idomeneo, King of Crete.
-That?
那真的是最平凡的作品
我也听过了
A tiresome piece. I heard it too.
最平凡的
Tiresome?
一个年轻人不自量力
太多的音符...
A young man trying to impress
beyond his abiIities.
Too much spice.
Too many notes.
陛下，我认为这是多年来
我听过最有潜力的作品
Majesty...
...it was the most promising work
I've heard in years.
也许我们应该想办法把他找来
WeII, then, we shouId make
some effort to acquire him.
维也纳也需要有一位
优秀的德国作曲家
We couId use a good German composer
in Vienna, sureIy?
只要价码合理
我相信他会有兴趣的
I'm sure he couId be tempted
with the right offer. Say...
为了我们的国家歌剧院
做一曲德文的歌剧
...an opera in German
for our NationaI Theater.
太好了，陛下
ExceIIent, sire!
不能用德文的，求求你，陛下
But not German. I beg, Your Majesty.
意大利文才是得体的歌剧语文
ItaIian is the proper Ianguage
for opera.
这是知识份子的共识
AII educated peopIe agree on that.
内廷大臣，你认为怎么样
What do you think, chamberIain?
我认为现在该是
有国语歌剧的时候了
In my opinion, it's time
we had a piece in our own Ianguage.
让老百姓听德文
PIain German for pIain peopIe.
卡普麦斯特
Kapellmeister?
陛下，我赞成部长的看法
Majesty...
...I must agree with Herr Direttore.
德文...
German is...
真是失礼了
不够优雅，不适合歌剧
...too brute for singing.
御用作曲家，你的看法呢？
Court composer...
...what do you think?
我认为请莫札特来维也纳
是很有趣的构想
I think it's an interesting notion
to keep Mozart in Vienna.
这会使得大主教非常的愤怒
也许这是陛下的企图
It shouId infuriate the archbishop...
...if that is Your Majesty's
intention.
你说对了，御用作曲家
You are cattivo, court composer.
我要见见这位年轻人
I want to meet this young man.
内廷大臣
为他安排一个欢迎会
Arrange a pIeasant weIcome for him.
就这样子了
WeII, there it is!
谢谢主
这顶假发太适合你了
看起来实在太棒了
This is a beautifuI wig for you.
我真的好喜欢
It Iooks so marveIous and I Iove it.
换一顶
The other one.
这就是另一顶
我想你一定会喜欢的
Here is the other one.
I think you wiII Iove it.
就是这个样子
Here's the third one. So? Here we go.
你觉得怎么样
这些都好漂亮
-How do you Iike it?
-They're aII so beautifuI!
我为什么没有三个头
Why don't I have three heads?
真是幽默...
This is funny!
Three heads!
各位，早安
陛下，早安
怎么样
GentIemen.
-Good morning.
-Morning, Your Majesty.
今天为我准备了什么
What do you have for me today?
陛下，莫札特先生
-Your Majesty, Herr Mozart.
怎么样
-Yes, what about him?
他来了
He's here.
就这样子了，很好
WeII, there it is. Good!
陛下，希望您不会觉得不得体
可是我写了一首歌欢迎他
I hope you won't find it improper,
but I've written a march in his honor.
这样真好，给我看看
What a charming idea, court composer.
May I see?
这只是一个小品
Just a....
Just a trifIe, of course.
我可以试试看吗
陛下...
May I try it?
我们来开心一下
Let's have some fun.
太棒了，御用作曲家
DeIightfuI, court composer!
他进来的时候
可不可以让我演奏
May I pIay it when he comes in?
那我真是太荣耀了，陛下
-You do me too much honor.
-Bring in Herr Mozart.
让莫札特先生进来
慢慢的...
But sIowIy.
我需要练习一下
I need a minute to practice.
C调...
很好，继续
Good, continue.
陛下，G调
G, Majesty.
太好了
ExceIIent!
Good, Majesty.
非常棒
Continue. Very good.
非常棒，陛下
Very good, Majesty.
节奏...
Tempo! Up.
轻轻的...有力的
再来一次，陛下
LightIy, then strongIy!
It's a march, Majesty.
Again.
太棒了，陛下...
Bravo, Majesty!
各位，请不要这么热情，谢谢
GentIemen, pIease.
A IittIe Iess enthusiasm, I beg you.
莫札特
陛下
这可不是圣物
No, pIease. It's not a hoIy reIic.
我们曾经见过面
就在这间房间里
You know, we have met before.
In this very room.
也许你不记得
那时候你只有6岁
You don't recaII. You were onIy 6.
那时候他演奏了最棒的协奏曲
He was giving a deIightfuI concert!
他从凳子上
爬下来时还滑了一跤
As he got off the stooI, he feII.
我的妹妹安东妮扶他起来
My sister Antoinette heIped him up.
你知道他做了什么吗
Know what he did?
他跳入她的怀中
问她，你愿不愿意嫁给我
He jumped into her arms and said,
''WiII you marry me? Yes or no?''
你一定认识这些男士
You know aII these gentIemen.
范史威登公爵
The Baron Van Swieten.
年轻人，我相当喜欢你的作品
谢谢
-I'm a great admirer of yours.
-Thank you.
卡普麦斯特
先生
Kapellmeister Bonno.
我的荣幸
The Director of Opera,
Count Orsini-Rosenberg.
我们的歌剧院长，罗森保伯爵
这绝对是我的荣幸
Sir, yes. The honor is mine,
absoIuteIy!
这是我们的御用作曲家
萨列里大师
Here is our
iIIustrious court composer...
...Maestro SaIieri.
这真的是令人喜悦
At Iast, such immense joy!
我很熟悉您的作品
I know your work weII.
我事实上修改过
您的一首作品
You know, I composed some variations
on a meIody of yours.
真的，哪一首
MIOCAROADONE
-ReaIIy? Which one?
-''Mio Caro Adone. ''
我真是受宠若惊
I'm fIattered.
这是一首奇怪的小品
不过有一些不错的结果
A funny tune,
but it yieIded some good things.
他现在回报了你的赞美
And now he has returned
the compIiment.
萨列里为你写了这首
欢迎你的进行曲
Herr Salieri composed
this IittIe march for you.
真的吗
ReaIIy?
谢谢你，先生
就是这样子了
现在我们来谈正事
WeII, there it is.
年轻人，我们要你写一出歌剧
你觉得怎么样
Down to business. We're going
to commission an opera from you.
What do you say?
陛下
我们最后有没有投票
决定德文还是意大利文
Did we vote in the end
for German or ItaIian?
陛下，最后我们是
倾向于意大利文的
Sire, if you remember,
we did finaIIy incIine to ItaIian.
是吗
Did we?
我认为这还没有决定，陛下
I don't think it was reaIIy decided,
Your Majesty.
拜托...我们写德文的
为什么
-German. PIease Iet it be German.
-Why so?
因为我已经找到最精彩的歌词
Because I've aIready found
the most wonderfuI Iibretto.
我有没有见过
Have I seen it?
院长阁下应该没有
I don't think you have, Herr Direktor.
这是很新的
我会立刻拿来给你看
It's quite new.-I'II show it to you immediateIy.
你最好赶快拿来
-I think you'd better.
介绍一下，介绍一下故事
WeII...
...teII us about it.
TeII us the story.
这是很有趣的，陛下
WeII, it's quite amusing, Majesty.
整个故事的背景...
It's set--
The whoIe thing is set in a....
在哪里
Yes? Where?
整个故事在妓院里发展
In a harem, Majesty.
In a seragIio.
你的意思是土耳其
没有错
-You mean in Turkey?
-Yes, exactIy.
那为什么要用德文
其实也不一定要
Then why especiaIIy
does it have to be in German?
如果你们喜欢的话
也可以用土耳其文
It doesn't, especiaIIy. It couId be
in Turkish if you reaIIy want.
亲爱的朋友
语文已经不是重点了
No, my dear feIIow, the Ianguage
is not finaIIy the point.
你认为这个主题
很适合国家剧院吗
Do you reaIIy think that subject
is appropriate for a nationaI theater?
有何不可，故事很精彩
Why not? It's charming.
我又不会真的让妓女露出...
I mean, I won't actuaIIy show
concubines exposing their....
这绝对不是非礼的
这是非常崇高的，陛下
It's not indecent.
It's highIy moraI, Majesty.
充满了德意志精神与价值观
It's fuII of proper German virtues.
对不起，陛下
什么是德意志精神
Excuse me, Majesty, but what
do you think these couId be?
我是一个外国人
我想要学习
Being a foreigner, I'd Iove to Iearn.
告诉他，莫札特
什么是德意志精神
WeII, teII him, Mozart.
Name us a German virtue.
爱，陛下
-Love, sire.
-Oh, Iove!
当然是爱
我们意大利人不懂爱
Of course, in ItaIy
we know nothing about Iove.
我不认为你们懂
No, I don't think you do.
看意大利歌剧时
那么多的高音在吼，尖叫
Watching ItaIian opera,
aII those maIe sopranos screeching...
一对肥胖的情侣
在那里翻白眼，抛媚眼
...fat coupIes roIIing their eyes
about.
那不是爱情，那是垃圾
That's not Iove. It's rubbish!
陛下，你选择语文
Majesty, you choose the Ianguage.
我的责任是
使这成为最优秀的歌剧
I'II set it to the finest music
ever offered a monarch.
就这样子了
WeII, there it is.
那就选德文吧
Let it be German.
这是你的
This is yours.
留下来吧，陛下
这已经印在我的脑中了
Keep it.
It's aIready here in my head.
你只有听过一次
我想是吧，陛下
What? On one hearing onIy?
I think so, sire. Yes.
秀给我们看
Show us.
其余的都是一样的，是不是
The rest is the same, isn't it?
这里好像不太顺
Doesn't reaIIy work, does it?
你有没有试过...
Did you try...?
是不是应该比较...
ShouIdn't it be a bit more...?
这样子比较好...对...就这样
Or this?
This. Yes.
好听吗？你们认为如何
Better?
What do you think?
谢谢主
我所要的只是歌颂上帝
All I ever wanted
was to sing to God.
她给了我这种欲望
可是又使我哑巴
He gave me that Ionging...
...and then made me mute.
Why?
为什么，告诉我
TeII me that.
如果她不要我用音乐去赞美她
If he didn't want me
to praise him with music...
为什么要给我欲望
...why impIant the desire...
就好像是生理上的欲望
却又不给我才华
...Iike a Iust in my body?
And then deny me the taIent?
卡瓦里瑞夫人来上课了，大师
Madame CavaIieri is here
for her Iesson, sir.
Maestro.
怎么样
WeII...?
你喜欢吗
How do you Iike it?
这是土耳其式的
It's Turkish.
我的美发师说
今年流行的是土耳其风格
My hairdresser said everything
this year's going to be Turkish.
是吗
Does he?
他今天还告诉你什么
What eIse did he teII you today?
告诉我最新的传闻
Come, come!
Give me some gossip.
听说你见过莫札特先生
WeII, I heard you met Herr Mozart.
维也纳的消息传的真快
News traveIs fast in Vienna.
听说他被聘用要写一出歌剧
And he's been commissioned
to write an opera. Is it true?
是的
-Yes.
有没有留给我的角色
没有
-Is there a part in it for me?
-No.
你怎么知道
-How do you know?
你知道故事的剧情是什么吗
-Do you know where it's set, my dear?
-Where?
是什么
妓院
In a harem.
那是什么
妓女院
-What's that?
-A brotheI.
来，我们开始吧
Come.
Let's begin.
他的外表怎么样
莫札特吗
-What does he Iook Iike?
-Mozart?
你也许会失望
为什么
-You might be disappointed.
-Why?
外表与才华往往不是搭配的
Looks and taIent don't aIways
go together, Katerina.
我可不管外表，大师
Looks don't concern me, maestro.
有品味的女人在乎的只是才华
OnIy taIent interests
a woman of taste.
我们要不要继续
ShaII we continue?
她就在台上
There she was.
我不知道他们在哪儿认识
是怎么认识的
I don't know where they met or how.
There she stoodl
她就站在台上，给大家看
On stuge, for all to see.
像个贪婪的黄莺一样
炫耀给大家看
Showing off like
the greedy songbird she was.
十分钟的音阶
Ten minutes of ghastIy scaIes.
Arpeggios!
上上下下，好像游乐场的烟火
Whizzing up and down
like fireworks at a fairground.
请你了解
当时我爱上了这位小姐
Understand, I was
in Iove with the girI.
至少我渴望她
Or at Ieast in Iust.
可是我对你发誓
我碰都没有碰过她
And I swear to you,
I never Iaid a finger on her.
不管如何，我无法忍受
任何人去碰她
AII the same, I couIdn't bear
to think of anyone eIse touching her.
特别是那个怪物
Least of aII, ''the creature.''
快走...
太棒了，夫人
Brava, madame!
你真是我们舞台上的珠宝
You are an ornament to our stage.
陛下
Your Majesty.
莫札特先生，杰作
不，这真的是太杰出了
WeII, Herr Mozart.
A good effort.
WeII, decidedIy that.
你今天晚上令我们...
An exceIIent effort!
You have shown us something...
大开眼界
-...quite new tonight.
-It is new.
这是很新颖的，是不是
是的
-It is, isn't it, sire?
-Yes, indeed.
那您真的喜欢吗
当然喜欢，太精彩了
So then, you Iiked it?
You reaIIy Iiked it, sire?
WeII, of course I did!
It's very good!
只不过偶尔有一点...
Of course, now and then--
Just now and then...
...it seemed a touch....
您是什么意思，陛下
What do you mean, sire?
偶尔有一点...
WeII, I mean, occasionaIIy,
it seems to have....
这该怎么说
How shaII one say...?
这该怎么说，院长
How shaII one say, direktor?
太多的音符，陛下
正是
-Too many notes, Majesty?
-ExactIy. Very weII put.
说的好，太多的音符
-Too many notes.
-I don't understand.
我不了解，音符是我所要的
没有更多也没有更少
There are as many notes as
are required, neither more nor Iess.
亲爱的朋友，一个晚上
人只能听那么多的音符
My dear feIIow, there are in fact...
...onIy so many notes
the ear can hear in an evening.
我想这么说应该对吧
御用作曲家
I'm right in saying that,
aren't I, court composer?
是的...
Yes.
整体来说，是的，陛下
On the whoIe, yes, Majesty.
这真是太荒谬了
This is absurd!
年轻人，别难过
你的作品非常的杰出
Young man, don't take it too hard.
Your work is ingenious.
It's quaIity work.
只不过音符实在太多了
少一点音符就完美了
There are simpIy too many notes.
Just cut a few and it'II be perfect.
您希望少多少音符，陛下
Which few did you have in mind?
伍尔夫...亲爱的
WoIfgang!
WoIfgang, my dear!
伍尔夫
-WoIfgang!
-Majesty, this is Frau Weber.
陛下，这是韦伯夫人
她是我的房东
She's my IandIady.
荣幸，夫人
陛下，真是荣幸
-Enchanted, madame.
-Sire, such an honor!
这是我的女儿，康丝汀
她是莫札特先生的未婚妻
This is my dear daughter, Constanze.
-She's the fiancae of Herr Mozart.
真的吗
-ReaIIy?
真是迷人
How charming.
请
PIease.
怎么样
WeII,
你们什么时候要结婚
when do you marry?
这个...
我们还没有得到父亲的同意
We haven't exactIy received
my father's consent yet.
还没有万事具备
Not entireIy. Not aItogether.
对不起，你几岁了
26岁
-Excuse me, but how oId are you?
-Twenty-six.
我对你的建议是
娶了这位迷人的小姐
My advice is for you to marry
this charming young Iady...
和我们一起待在维也纳
-...and stay with us in Vienna.
-You see?
我对他说过了，陛下
可是他不听我的话
I toId him that,
but he won't Iisten to me.
陛下，你真的是提供了
这么棒的皇家建议
Your Majesty,
you give such wonderfuI...
我可不可以...
...such royaI advice. May I...?
就是这样子了
WeII, there it is.
可不可以去拿一点水来
Get some water!
请你拿一点水来
WiII you get some water, pIease?
伍尔夫，快拿水来
WoIfie, get some water!
借过...
Excuse me. Excuse me.
你知道这件事吗？
Did you know?
知道什么？
-What?
这个婚事
-The marriage.
这跟你有何关系？
What does it matter to you?
没关系，我才不管他要娶谁
Nothing. He can marry who he pIeases,
I don't give a damn.
我表现的如何？
How was I?
实在太好了
You were subIime.
你觉得曲写得好吗
And what did you think of the music?
非常的棒
ExtremeIy cIever.
卡夫人，我...
Katerina, I--
对不起
Excuse me.
那个肥女人还躺在舞台上吗
Is that woman stiII Iying
on the fIoor?
醒了，没事
-No, she's fine.
那我就放心了
-Oh, I'm so reIieved.
莫札特，我衷心的恭喜你
Dear Mozart,
my sincere congratuIations.
你喜欢吗
-Did you Iike it then?
我爱极了
-How couId I not?
这可说是世界级的水准，是吗
It's the best music
in Vienna today, agree?
她的床上功夫一定非常棒
She must be dazzIing in bed.
我想她还是个处女吧
I assume she's the virtuoso
in that department.
否则你怎么会
想要娶这样的女人呢
No other reason why
you'd marry someone Iike that.
请进
Come in.
打扰了，妈妈觉得不舒服
Excuse me.
WoIfie, Mom isn't feeIing very weII.
我们可以回家了吗？
当然
-Can we go home?
-Yes.
不...他还不能走呢
今天是他的好日子
No, no, no.
You can't take him away now.
This is his night.
你不介绍一下未婚妻吗？
Won't you introduce us, WoIfgang?
失陪了，晚安，各位
Excuse us, Fraulein.
Good night.
那一刻我就知道
毫无疑问地，他掌握了她
At that moment I knew,
beyond any doubt...
...he'd had her.
那个怪物夺走了我的宝贝
The creature had
had my darling girl.
这真的是无法理解
It was incomprehensibIe!
上帝到底有何意图
What was God up to?
上帝是否在测试我？
Was it possibIe I was being tested?
想要让我了解宽恕的意义
而不要心生攻击
Was God expecting me
to offer forgiveness...
...in the face of every offense?
不管有多么地痛苦
No matter how painfuI?
这很有可能
It's very possibIe.
But why him?
为何是他，选他来测试我
太没人性了
Why choose Mozart
to teach me Iessons in humiIity?
我心中充满了
对那年轻人的恨意
My heart was fiIIing up...
...with such hatred
for that IittIe man.
这是我一生中第一次
心中有了残暴的想法
For the first time in my Iife,
I began to know...
...reaIIy...
...vioIent thoughts.
每天，甚至隔几个小时
我就祷告
Every day, sometimes for hours,
I would pray.
主啊，请求你，让他走吧
Lord...
...pIease...
...send him away...
就此打住
...back to SaIzburg.
为了他好，也是为了我好
For his sake...
...as weII as mine.
不，我不接纳他
阁下
-No! I won't have him back.
-But, Your Grace--
你的儿子没有道德
被宠坏了，自大
Your son is an unprincipIed,
spoiIed, conceited brat!
阁下，这是事实
Yes, sir...
...that is the truth.
可是不要责怪他
这全都是我的错
But don't bIame him.
The fauIt is mine, entireIy.
我太宠他了
I was too induIgent with him.
求求你，阁下
再给他一次机会
PIease, Your Grace?
Give him one more chance?
我准许你去试试看
上帝保佑您，阁下
You have Ieave to try.
God bIess, Your Grace!
I thank Your Grace.
感谢您，阁下
I thank you!
我有紧急的要事告诉你
我要来维也纳了
I write to you with urgent news.
I'm coming to Vienna.
直到我们见面
不准进行婚事
Take no further steps
towards marriage until we meet.
我是把一生都奉献给你的父亲
请你等待我的来临
As you honor the father who has
devoted his life to yours...
...do as I bid,
and await my coming.
我宣布你们二人结为夫妻
I now join you in the hoIy bonds
of matrimony.
上帝所结合的二人
没有任何人能够拆散
Those whom God hath joined together...
...Iet no man put asunder.
以天父，天子，圣灵之名
亲爱的父亲，你曾经说过
维也纳是音乐家的城市
Beloved father:
能够征服这里
就是征服全欧洲
You say Vienna is the musicians' city.
To conquer here is to conquer Europe.
有了我的妻子
现在我办得到
With my wife I can do it.
不久后，当我发财了
One day, when I'm wealthy...
你可以过来和我们一起住
我们会非常的快乐
...you'll come and live with us,
and we'll be so happy.
早安，御用作曲家
这是我的侄女伊莉莎白公主
Good morning.
This is my niece, Princess EIizabeth.
殿下
Your Highness.
她请我去见一位音乐老师
我有了一个很好的构想
She's asked me to recommend
a musicaI instructor.
-I've come up with an exceIIent idea.
-Your Majesty!
陛下，这真的是我的荣幸
It wouId be such a tremendous honor!
我本来想的是莫札特先生
你有什么看法
I was thinking of Herr Mozart.
What is your view?
这个构想很有趣，可是...
怎么说
It's an interesting idea, Majesty.
But....
Yes?
我所关切的是
免得您被人们说闲话
My concern is to protect you...
...from any hint of favoritism.
徇私
Favoritism.
怎么了，内廷大臣
什么怎么了
-What is this?
-What is what?
为什么我的作品要送交委员会
又要教一个13岁女孩音乐
Why must I submit sampIes of my work
to a committee, to teach a girI?
这是陛下的旨意
Because His Majesty wishes it.
陛下生了我的气吗
Is the emperor angry with me?
正好相反
那他为什么不指派我
-On the contrary.
-Then why not appoint me to the post?
莫札特，你不是
维也纳唯一的作曲家
Mozart, you're not
the onIy composer in Vienna.
没错，可是我是最好的
No. But I'm the best.
莫札特
Mozart.
谦虚一点对你也许比较好
A IittIe modesty
might suit you better.
委员会有哪一些委员
Who is on this committee?
卡普麦斯特，罗森保伯爵
还有御用作曲家萨列里
Kapellmeister Bonno, Count
Orsini-Rosenberg and SaIieri.
当然，那些意大利人
总是那些意大利人
NaturaIIy, the ItaIians!
Of course, aIways the ItaIians!
他们都是音乐白痴
They're aII musicaI idiots!
你要他们来评论我的音乐
-And you want them to judge my music?
-Young man...
年轻人，问题很简单
...the issue is quite simpIe.
If you want this position...
如果你要这份职位
和同行一起拿出作品送审
...you must submit your stuff
aIong with aII your coIIeagues.
我必须吗
Must I?
我不干
WeII, I won't.
我们要如何过活呢，伍尔夫？
How are we supposed to Iive?
你要我上街乞讨吗？
Do you want me to beg on the streets?
笨蛋
Don't be stupid.
他们只是想要看你的作品
-AII they want to see is your work.
-Shit.
那样有什么不好
-What's wrong with that?
闭嘴，给我闭嘴
-Shut up! Just shut up.
那些皇家贵族
怎么可能来求你呢？
One royaI pupiI,
and aII of Vienna wiII come fIocking.
他们就是会来的
They'II come anyway.
不会的
-No, they won't.
他们喜欢我
-They Iove me here.
我知道这里行事规范
-I know how things work in this city.
你真是个万事通
-You know everything.
对不起
-Yes?
-Excuse me, sir.
外面有一位女子要见您
-A Iady insists on taIking to you.
是谁？
不知道
-Who?
She didn't say,
她说有紧急的事情要见您
but she says it's urgent.
失陪一下，亲爱的
Excuse me, my dear.
先生阁下
Your ExceIIency.
我能帮你什么忙
How can I heIp you?
莫札特太太
-Frau Mozart?
我是为了我丈夫来的
-I've come on behaIf of my husband.
我带来他的作品
让他有机会得到皇室的工作
I brought sampIes of his work so he
can be considered for the appointment.
这真的是太好了
他为什么没有自己来
How charming,
but why did he not come himseIf?
先生，他非常的忙
He's terribIy busy, sir.
这个我了解
I understand.
我一有时间我就会看
这是我的荣幸
I'II Iook at them the moment I can.
请代我向他致意
It wiII be an honor.
PIease give him my warmest regards.
如果你现在就看会不会太麻烦
WouId it be too much troubIe
to ask you to Iook at them now?
我在这里等
-WhiIe I wait.
-I'm afraid I'm not at Ieisure...
我现在这一刻恐怕没有时间
...this precise moment.
放在我这里
我保证一定会很安全的
Leave them.
I assure you, they wiII be safe.
我恐怕不能这么做
I reaIIy cannot do that, sir.
他不知道我来了
你不是他派来的
You see, he doesn't know I'm here.
He didn't send you?
不是，这是我的想法
No, sir. This was my own idea.
我明白了
-I see.
-Sir, we're desperate.
先生，我们穷途末路了
我们真的需要这份工作
We reaIIy need this job.
我的先生花的钱
超出他所赚到的
My husband spends far more
than he can ever earn.
我不是说他懒懒
他一点都不懒
I don't mean that he's Iazy,
because he works aII day Iong.
他一整天都在工作
只是他不实际
It's just that he's not practicaI.
他就是守不住钱
这真是太可笑了
Money simpIy sIips through
his fingers. It's ridicuIous.
要不要吃点糖
你知道这是什么吗
Let me offer you some refreshment.
Do you know what these are?
这是维娜斯的乳头
Capezzoli di Venere!
NippIes of Venus.
这是包白兰地糖的核桃
你吃一颗
They're Roman chestnuts in brandied
sugar. Try one. Go on, try one!
吃吃看，非常的美味
They're quite surprising.
好好吃
They're wonderfuI!
谢谢你，阁下
不要这么叫我
Thank you very much, Your ExceIIency.
Don't keep caIIing me that.
这样子有距离感
Keeps me at such a distance.
我不是一出生
就是御用作曲家的
I wasn't born a court composer,
you know.
我和你丈夫一样都是小镇人
I'm from a smaII town.
Just Iike your husband.
你确定你不能留下这个
稍后再回来
Are you sure you can't...
...Ieave this and come back again?
虽然听起来很不错
可是这是不可能的
It's very tempting, sir.
But it's impossibIe, I'm afraid.
如果他知道这不见了
他一定会发疯的
He'd be frantic
if he knew they were missing.
这是原稿
You see, they're aII originaIs.
原稿
他从来不会复写
-OriginaIs?
-Yes, sir. He doesn't make copies.
这些是原稿
These...
...are originaIs?
太不可思议了
那根本超越理解
Astoundingl
It was actuaIIy--
It was beyond beIief.
这是唯一的版本
These were first and onIy...
...drafts of music.
完全没有任何的修正
But they showed no corrections
of any kind.
一点都没有
Not one.
他只是写出脑中的音乐
He had simply written down music...
...aIready finished in his head.
一页接着一页
好像他在听写一样
Page after page of it.
As if he were just taking dictation.
而这是前所未见的悦耳音乐
And music...
...finished as no music
is ever finished.
换了一个音符就不完美
DispIace one note...
...and there wouId be diminishment.
换了一段音节
结构就会瓦解
DispIace one phrase,
the structure wouId faII.
我现在了解在大主教公馆
所听到的音乐不是意外
It was clear to me...
...that sound I had heard
in the archbishop's palace...
...had been no accident.
我又听到了上帝的天籁
Here again
was the very voice of God.
我透过音符所架成的铁笼看到
I was staring through the cage...
...of those meticuIous ink strokes...
最纯粹的美
...at an absoIute beauty.
这个不够好吗
Is it not good?
这简直太棒了
It is miracuIous!
是的，他对他的作品引以为傲
Yes, he's very proud of his work.
你会帮助我们吗
So you wiII heIp us?
明晚我与陛下共进晚餐时
可以帮他提一下
I dine with the emperor
tomorrow evening.
One word from me and the post is his.
谢谢，阁下
Thank you, Your ExceIIency!
Thank you!
今晚再过来
Come back tonight.
晚上？
-Tonight?
独自过来
-AIone.
为什么？
What for?
天下没有白吃的晚餐
Some service
deserves service in return.
懂吗？
No?
什么意思？
-What do you mean?
-Isn't it obvious?
还不明白吗？这是游戏规则
It's a post aII Vienna seeks.
如果你想帮你丈夫
晚上再过来
If you wish it for your husband,
come tonight.
我是已婚妇人
I'm a married woman, sir.
那就不要来了
Then don't.
随便你
It's up to you.
没有付出那有收获
And not to be vague,
that is the price.
这不是上帝的怜悯
There is no God of mercy, Father.
上帝是要折磨我
Just a God of torture.
夜晚到来了
Evening came.
我真希望她不要来了
I sat there,
not knowing whether she'd return.
我从未如此认真的祈祷
I prayed as I have
never prayed before.
亲爱的上帝
Dear God...
给予我能力
让我写出真正的音乐
...enter me now.
Fill me with one piece of true music.
让我知道你还是会眷顾我的
One piece with your breath in it,
so I know that you love me.
让我感受你的爱
也让我能回馈你
Show me one sign of your favor,
and I will show mine to Mozart.
我就会协助莫札特进入委员会
I will get him the royal position.
给我能力，请求你
Enter me.
PIease.
请求你
PIease!
什么事？
Yes?
那位女士又来了
That Iady is back, sir.
请她进来
Show her in.
怎样
WeII?
我来了
I'm here.
我先生去听音乐会
My husband has gone to a concert.
He didn't think I wouId enjoy it.
我们要去哪里
WeII, where shaII we go?
在这里吗
ShouId we stay here?
WeII....
你还要看这作品吗？
You stiII want to Iook at these?
或是可以省了
Or don't we need to bother anymore?
因为不需要这样看了...
Suppose we don't, reaIIy.
把这个女人赶出去
Show this woman out.
亲爱的
Stanzi.
怎么了
What is it?
什么事情？
What's the matter?
告诉我
TeII me.
我爱你...
I Iove you.
从此以后我们誓不两立
From now on, we are enemies.
你和我
You and I.
因为你选择了自大，色情，下流
幼稚的男孩做为你的工具
You choose for your instrument...
...a boastful, lustful,
smutty, infantile boy...
你所给我的奖励
是让我能够了解他的才华
...and give me for reward only the
ability to recognize the incarnation.
因为你不公道，不公平
Because you are unjust...
...unfair...
不仁慈，我拒绝你
...unkind...
...I will block you.
我发誓，我要去伤害
你在世上的代言人
I swear it.
我要尽我的能力去害他
我要毁了你的工具
I will hinder and harm
your creature on earth...
...as far as I am able.
陛下，我不是个爱说
说别的音乐家坏话的人
I don't Iike to taIk
against a feIIow musician.
当然
Of course not.
我必须向您禀报
I have to teII you.
年轻的女孩子是不能
与莫札特独处在一起
Mozart is not entireIy to be trusted
aIone with young Iadies.
真的吗？
ReaIIy?
事实上，我有一位学生
非常年轻的女声乐家
One of my own pupiIs,
a very young singer...
卡瓦里瑞夫人告诉我，她...
...Maria Theresa Paradis...
...toId me she was....
WeII....
说了什么？
WeII, what?
至少已经跟她发生两次的关系
MoIested, Majesty.
Twice, in the course of
the same Iesson.
主人，莫札特先生在书房等您
There is a Herr Mozart
waiting for you in the saIon.
他们选了谁？
-Whom did they choose?
桑摩
-Herr Zummer.
Herr Zummer?
他只是个平庸的人
But the man's a fooI!
He's a totaI mediocrity.
不...他连平庸都不如
No, no. He has yet
to achieve mediocrity.
无论如何
我一定要争取到这个职位
I can't Iose this post.
I simpIy can't.
阁下，拜托，我们去面圣
告诉陛下，选桑摩是大错特错
ExceIIency, pIease.
Let's go to the paIace.
You can taIk to the emperor...
...and teII him that Herr Zummer
is an awfuI choice.
这对伊莉莎白公主的音乐品味
影响甚巨
He couId do musicaI harm
to the princess.
私底下老实跟你说
公主根本没有音乐品味
Between us, no one in the worId
couId do musicaI harm to the princess.
这样
Look...
我必须要教学生了
否则我活不下去了
...I must have pupiIs.
Without pupiIs, I can't manage.
你的生活不是一切如常吗
You don't mean
you're Iiving in poverty?
没有，我已经破产了
No, but I'm broke.
这怎么可能呢？
WeII, how is this possibIe?
你所写的作品都很成功啊
I hear your concerts are
quite successfuI.
就是因为太成功了
They're stupendousIy successfuI.
这无法得到工作
You can't get a seat.
问题就是没人有意愿请我
The troubIe is, no one wiII hire me.
只想听我弹奏，不敢请我教音乐
觉得我太神圣了
They won't Iet me teach their
daughters, as if I was a fiend.
说真格的
您是否可以借我一些钱呢
SeriousIy...
...is there any chance
you couId manage a Ioan?
只要六个月
或是八个月之后就还你
OnIy for six months.
Eight, at the most.
你是说八个月后你就会变富有了
You expect your fortunes to change
in six or eight months?
事实上是真的
As a matter of fact, I do.
我现在脑子里面
有个爆炸性的作品
I am working on something that wiII
expIode Iike a bomb aII over Europe.
一旦完成
我就会变成维也纳最富有的人
I'II be the richest man in Vienna.
到时我就可以加倍奉还
I'II pay you back doubIe.
你说要几倍都可以
You name the terms.
这真好
WeII, how exciting.
告诉我你在做什么
TeII me more.
抱歉，这是个小秘密
It's a bit of a secret.
说啊...我很有兴趣
-Come, come. I'm interested.
这真好吃，是什么点心？
-This is deIicious. What is it?
这是奶油起司
Cream cheese mixed with sugar...
加上一颗一颗的糖，打起泡泡
极品，真的很好吃
...suffused with rum.
Crema Mascarpone Speciale.
真不错
ItaIian.
当然
每个人都喜欢自己国家的食品
Forgive me. We aII have
patriotic feeIings of some kind.
我...只需要200元
Two thou--
Two hundred fIorins.
That's aII I need.
100元就好
A hundred.
50元好了
Fifty.
你到底在做什么？
What exactIy are you working on?
我...
我实在不能告诉你？
ReaIIy, I can't say.
在维也纳你不能只光靠
莫札特三个字行走
I don't think you shouId become known
in Vienna as a debtor, Mozart.
尽管如此，我可以介绍个人
给你认识，他有个女儿
However...
...I know a distinguished
gentIeman I can recommend, and...
...he has a daughter.
安静
Quiet! Quiet!
莫札特
Herr Mozart.
他们太紧张了，不要理他们
WeIcome. Pay no attention,
they're impossibIe.
我待他们就像自己的孩子一般
I treat them just Iike
my own chiIdren.
我要教哪一个？
Which of them do you
wish me to teach?
好笑
That's funny.
你真是幽默
You're a funny feIIow.
这里就是音乐房
This is the instrument.
我希望你会满意
I hope it wiII be to your satisfaction.
他当然会满意
Of course it'II be
to his satisfaction.
来吧...我们来听音乐
过来...来
Come, we're going to Iisten
to some music. Come!
Good boy.
好了
Now.
现在弹你最擅长的
PIease pIay me something,
just to give me an idea.
随便你弹
Anything wiII do.
弹吧，简单地弹一弹
Just go ahead.
Just as if we weren't here.
就当我们是音乐厅的观众
是不是这样
Part of music, getting used
to an audience. Right, Herr Mozart?
或许让我们独自在此弹奏就好
我们都很害羞
Perhaps it wouId be better
if we were Ieft aIone.
We're both a IittIe shy.
弹吧，叫你弹
麦可，不要这样
PIay.
-I said pIay!
-MichaeI, pIease.
或许我应该先来示范一曲
Perhaps if I pIay first,
it might encourage the Fraulein.
Why don't you Iet me try?
不要叫
Stop it! Stop!
每次听到音乐就叫
He aIways howIs when he hears music.
受不了你，真是的
不要叫了，宝贝
We've got to break him of that habit.
We've got to break them
of their habit!
请弹吧...莫札特，请弹
PIay. PIease.
Herr Mozart, pIay.
PIease, I beg you.
就这样
That's it.
乖
继续弹
Keep pIaying!
继续弹，就这样
That's it!
好棒
好乖...
莫札特，太好了
Mozart, that's wonderfuI!
WonderfuI!
如果还需要用音乐指导你的狗
请再通知我
Next time you wish me to instruct
another of your dogs, Iet me know.
再见，再见了各位
Goodbye, Fraulein. Goodbye, madam.
Goodbye, sir.
爸爸
Papa?
Papa!
你到这里做什么？
Why are you here?
我不能来吗？
Am I not weIcome?
当然可以来，爸爸，欢迎...
Of course, weIcome.
Papa, weIcome! WeIcome!
你好瘦
You're thin.
你的太太难道不喂你吗
Doesn't your wife feed you?
她当然会喂好
一整天好像填鸭子一样
Feed! Of course she feeds me.
She stuffs me Iike a goose, aII day!
她不在家吗
-Is she not here?
-No, she had to heIp her mother.
她要去帮母亲的忙
她就是这样的人
She's Iike that.
她母亲是个很好的人
Her mother's a very sweet woman.
我不知道你在家
I didn't know you were home.
史坦丝，这是我的父亲
Stanzi, this is my father.
我们等一下...
We'II wait. We'II wait.
你现在起床好吗，达令
Why don't you get up now, my darIing?
她实在是累死了
可怜的女人
She's very tired, poor creature.
你也知道我懒的要死
我很邋遢
You know me.
I'm such a pig.
帮我打扫可不是一件容易的事
It's not easy cIeaning up after me.
你们难道没有女佣吗
Don't you have a maid?
没有，我们想要的话也可以有
Oh. No.
但是史坦丝不愿意
她坚持一切都要自己做
We couId if we wanted...
...but Stanzi insists on doing
everything herseIf.
你们的经济方面怎么样
不可能更好了
How is your...
...financiaI situation?
CouIdn't be better.
这和我昨天说的不一样
这是什么意思
That's not what I hear.
What do you mean?
一切都很好
It's wonderfuI.
真的，这里的人非常喜欢我
ReaIIy, it's marveIous!
PeopIe Iove me here.
他们说你欠了很多钱
They say you have debts.
是谁？
Who?
谁说的
Who says that?
这是恶意的谎言
That's a maIicious Iie!
你有学生吗
Do you have pupiIs?
我不要学生，他们会防碍我
I don't want pupiIs!
They get in the way.
我必须空出时间来作曲
I have to have time for composition.
作曲是赚不到钱的
你也知道的
Composition doesn't pay.
You know that.
这首可以赚的到
That one wiII.
那是什么
What's that?
秘密
It's a secret.
什么秘密，你不需要对我保密
Secret?
You don't have secrets from me.
不...
No, no, no!
拜托你，我不要你看
我不要任何人看
PIease! I don't want anyone to see it.
但是你一定
会为我骄傲的，爸爸
You'II be so proud of me.
这即将是我最棒的杰作
这是有史以来最...
It's going to be the
best thing that I've ever done.
她来了，看看她
她是不是最美的人
There she is!
Look at her!
Isn't she beautifuI?
爸爸，承认吧
她是不是最美丽的媳妇
Confess it.
-CouId you want a prettier daughter?
别闹了...
-Stop it, WoIfie!
我看起来糟糕极了
I Iook dreadfuI.
你是不是怀孕了
是的
Are you expecting?
是不是棒极了
我们非常的高兴
-Yes, I am.
-Isn't it marveIous? We're deIighted.
莫札特先生
可不可以帮你倒杯茶
-May I offer you some tea?
茶，谁要喝茶，我们出去吧
-Who wants tea? Let's go out!
我们应该吃大餐
你不会想喝茶吧，爸爸
This caIIs for a feast.
You don't want tea, do you?
我知道，我们去跳舞
爸爸热爱宴会
I know! Let's go dancing.
Papa Ioves parties, don't you?
伍尔夫
什么，真是无聊，喝茶
How can you be so boring? Tea!
Come on, Papa. Hurry!
Here we go. Good day.
现在...
Now!
我来决定怎么处罚...
I name the penaIty!
我们的处罚方法是
想一个好一点的
And the penaIty is....
把腿露出来
-Give her a good one!
-Show us your Iegs!
快一点...
Come on, come on!
这只是个游戏，爸爸
It's just a game, Papa.
谢谢
现在...
不...
莫札特先生
你来决定儿子的处罚
Herr Mozart, why don't you
name your son's penaIty?!
爸爸，你来决定吧
Yes, Papa. Name it.
你要什么我都照办
随便什么都可以
I'II do anything you say. Anything.
我要你和我回去沙兹堡，儿子
I want you to come back
to SaIzburg with me.
爸爸，规则是
处罚必须在这里能够执行
The penaIty must be
performed in the room.
我觉得这个游戏很无聊
我不想玩下去了
I'm tired of this game.
我的处罚是什么...
必须要处罚我...
But my penaIty!
I've got to have a penaIty!
我来决定处罚...
I name a penaIty!
你的处罚是用巴哈的风格
来演奏我们的小调
The penaIty is...
...you shaII pIay our tune...
...in the manner of
Johann Sebastian Bach!
现在把他翻过来...
Turn him over!
让他翻过来弹琴
Now you pIay it backwards!
再来一曲...
Another one! Give me another one!
和格拉克一样的演奏
无聊
PIay Iike GIuck!
Boring. Another!
演奏韩德尔
我不喜欢他，换一个
HandeI!
I don't Iike him! Another one!
演奏萨列里的
PIay SaIieri.
这可是一个挑战
Now that is a chaIIenge!
That is a chaIIenge.
请让让...
PIease! PIease!
继续吧，取笑我吧，笑吧
Go on. Mock me. Laugh!
笑我的不是莫札特
是上帝，神父
That was not Mozart Iaughing, Father.
That was God.
那是上帝
透过那荒唐的笑声取笑我
That was God Iaughing at me
through that obscene giggIe.
继续笑吧，先生
Go on, signore.
Laugh.
笑我，把我的平庸
展现给大家看
Show my mediocrity for aII to see.
有一天我会笑你的
One day I wiII Iaugh at you.
在我离开人世之前
我会笑你的
Before I Ieave this earth...
...I wiII Iaugh at you.
伍尔夫
-WoIfie?
什么事
-What?
有一个小女孩要找你
There's a young girI here to see you.
她有什么事
What does she want?
她不愿意对我说
她说，她有话要对你说
She won't taIk to me.
She says she has to speak to you.
该死
Damn.
什么事
Yes?
你是莫札特先生吗
是的
-Are you Herr Mozart?
-That's right.
我的名字是萝拉
我是一个女佣
My name is LorI, sir.
I'm a maidservant.
我被指派来这里为您服务
I was asked to come here
and offer my services to you.
你的崇拜者愿意出钱
但是他希望能够匿名
They'II be paid for by an admirer
of yours who wishes to remain...
...anonymous.
这是你的主意吗，爸爸
Is this your idea, Papa?
我的主意？
Mine?
你是不是在和我开玩笑
-Are you pIaying a trick on me?
我这一辈子没见过这个女孩
-I've never seen this girI.
这是某种玩笑吗
不是的，先生
-Is this a joke?
-Not at aII, sir.
小女孩，这是不可能的
Young woman, this won't do.
我的儿子不可能接受这种做法
不管这有多么的慷慨
My son can't accept such an offer,
no matter how generous...
除非他知道幕后的人是谁
可是我真的不能告诉你
-...unIess he knows who's behind it.
-I can't teII you that, sir.
这真的是太荒谬了
什么荒谬
-This is ridicuIous!
-What is ridicuIous?
伍尔夫在维也纳
有许多的崇拜者
WoIfie has many admirers in Vienna.
大家都很喜欢他
总是有人送我们礼物
PeopIe send us gifts aII the time.
但是没有调查清楚
不能够把她留下来
You cannot accept her
without references.
这不关你的事
派你来的人会付薪水吧
This is none of your business.-Whoever sent you is going to pay?
没有错，夫人
太好了
-That's right.
SpIendid!
现在我们要让一个陌生人
进入我们的家
Now we're going
to Iet a stranger into our house.
谁是我们...
Who is we?
Who is Ietting who--?
请你在外面等一下
好的，夫人
-CouId you pIease wait outside?
-Yes, ma'am.
老头子，我们在你身上
花了很多的钱
Look, oId man!
你只会从早到晚抱怨
We spend a fortune on you,
and aII you do is criticize.
现在你认为...
史坦丝
-And now--
-Stanzi!
No! He shouId hear!
不，他应该要听到
我真的是感到很厌倦了
I'm sick to death of it.
我们为你做什么
你都不会觉得满意
We can't do anything
right for you, can we?
你们再也不必为我做事了
You won't have to do anything
for me ever again.
我走了
I'm Ieaving.
不要，爸爸
-No, Papa.
别担心
我不会待在这里拖累你们
-I won't stay and be a burden.
没有人认为你是负担
她认为是
No one caIIs you that.
她说我只会一整天睡觉
She does.
She says I sIeep aII day.
你也差不多啊
你只会离开房间吃东西
And so you do!
The onIy time you come out is to eat.
你期待什么呢
WeII, what do you expect?
你觉得人们应该每天走进
这么脏的屋子里吗
Do you expect anyone to waIk out
into a mess Iike this every day?
现在要说我不会管家了
事实上如此
-Now I'm a bad housekeeper!
-So you are. It's a pigsty.
你何时可以上班？
When can you start?
现在
-Right away, ma'am.
-Good.
每天晚上开派对
They're out every night, sir.
谢谢你，先生
Thank you, sir.
家里有没有学生上门
Do any pupiIs come to the house?
我没有见过
Not that I've seen.
那他怎么会有钱花
Then how does he pay for aII this?
他有工作吗
Does he work at aII?
有，一整天的工作
Yes, sir. AII day Iong.
他要等到晚上才会出门
He never Ieaves untiI evening.
他坐在那里不停的写
真的吗
He just sits there,
writing and writing.
ReaIIy!
他在写什么
What is he writing?
这个我不知道，先生
当然不知道
I wouIdn't know that, sir.
Of course not.
你是个好女孩
你为我这么做太好了
You're a good girI.
You're very kind to do this.
下一次你确定他们不在家时
Next time you're sure
they'II be out...
让我知道
...Iet me know.
谢谢你，先生
Thank you, sir.
我想我发现了钱的事情
I think I found out
about the money, sir.
怎么说
Yes? What?
他这里有七个鼻烟盒
我发誓这全都是纯金的
He kept seven snuffboxes in here.
I couId swear they were aII goId.
你看，现在只剩下一个了
And now Iook.
There's onIy one Ieft.
他在哪里工作
Where does he work?
在里面，先生
In there, sir.
费加洛的婚礼
各位，我听到了
各位会感兴趣的消息
I've just heard some news
that may be of interest to you.
什么新闻
What?
莫札特在写一出新的歌剧
意大利文的歌剧
Mozart is writing a new opera.
An ItaIian opera.
意大利文的...
ItaIian?
而且不只如此
他选择费加洛做为主角
That's not aII.
He has chosen for his subject, Figaro.
费加洛的婚礼
The Marriage of Figaro.
他要为那出舞台剧编曲
是的
He's setting that pIay to music?
Yes.
什么是费加洛的婚礼
What is this Marriage of Figaro?
那是一出法国的戏剧
是帝王禁止上演的
It's a French pIay, Kapellmeister.
It has been banned by the emperor.
你真的确定吗
You're absoIuteIy sure?
莫札特先生
各位请坐
GentIemen, sit down.
莫札特
Mozart.
你知不知道我宣布
法国戏剧费加洛的婚礼不得体
Are you aware that I have
decIared Figaro...
...unsuitabIe for our theater?
知道，陛下
Yes, sire.
我们听说你在写这出歌剧
这是不是事实
Yet we hear you're making an
opera from it. Is this true?
这是谁告诉你的，陛下
Who toId you this, Majesty?
现在你没有资格问问题
这是不是事实
It is not your pIace to ask questions.
Is it true?
是的...
Yes....
我承认
I admit it is.
你可不可以告诉我为什么
WouId you teII me why?
陛下，这只是一出喜剧
Majesty, it is onIy a comedy.
你的看法不是重点，莫札特
陛下的想法才重要
What you think
is scarceIy the point.
It's what His Majesty thinks
that counts.
可是，陛下
But, Your Majesty--
莫札特，我是一个有耐心的人
我不会随便下禁令的
Mozart...
...I am a toIerant man.
我做这种决定是有理由的
I do not censor things IightIy.
When I do, I have good reason.
费加洛的婚礼是不好的戏剧
挑拨阶级之间的冲突
Figaro is a bad pIay.
It stirs up hatred between cIasses.
在法国只有造成憎恨
In France, it has caused
onIy bitterness.
我的亲妹妹安东妮告诉我
她现在很害怕自己的子民
My sister Antoinette is beginning
to be frightened of her own peopIe.
陛下，我对你发誓
歌剧里没有这种成份
I swear, there's nothing Iike
that in the piece.
我把这些都删掉了
我憎恨政治
I've taken out everything that couId
give offense. I hate poIitics.
你可能有一点点幼稚
I'm afraid you're rather innocent.
在这种动荡的时期
In these dangerous times I cannot
afford to provoke our peopIe...
我不可能为了一出歌剧
影响到贵族以及子民
...simpIy over a theater piece.
陛下，这只是一出喜剧
主题是有关爱情的
Majesty, this is just a froIic.
A piece about Iove.
又是爱情
''Love.'' Again!
这是新的，全新的
And it's new!
It's entireIy new.
The peopIe wiII go mad for it.
这种事是会使人们疯狂的
我有一场戏
I have scenes....
比如说第二幕的最后
一开始是男女对唱
The end of act two, for exampIe.
只是一对夫妻在吵架
It starts as a duet.
A husband and wife quarreIing.
突然，有阴谋的女佣走进来
这是很有趣的情景
SuddenIy, the scheming maid comes in.
It's a very funny situation.
二重唱变成了三重唱
Duet turns into trio.
然后丈夫的侍者走进来
他与女佣有阴谋
Then the husband's vaIet comes in.
三重唱变成四重唱
Trio turns into quartet.
愚蠢的老园丁走进来
四重唱变成五重唱
Then a gardener.
Quartet becomes quintet.
然后不断的延伸下去...
And so on, on and on.
六重唱，七重唱，八重唱
Sextet, septet, octet.
你认为我可以维持多久，陛下
How Iong do you think
I can sustain that?
我不知道
你猜猜看...
I have no idea.
Guess.
Guess, Your Majesty.
想想看这种过程可以维持多久
然后再加一倍
Imagine the Iongest
it couId be sustained...
...then doubIe it.
WeII....
6...7分钟
Six...
...seven minutes?
8分钟
陛下，20分钟
-Eight minutes?
-Twenty, sire. Twenty minutes!
20分钟不断的音乐
完全没有对白
Twenty minutes of continuous music.
No recitatives!
陛下，这是只有歌剧办的到的
Sire, onIy opera can do this.
在戏剧中如果不只一个人说话
In a pIay, if more than one person
speaks at once...
那就只能听的到噪音
没有人可以了解一句对话
...it's just noise.
可是透过歌剧，或是音乐
But with opera, with music...
音乐可以让20个人
同时的说话
...you can have 20 individuaIs
aII taIking at the same time.
这不只不是噪音
而且是完美的旋律
It's not noise.
It's a perfect harmony!
莫札特，重点不是音乐
没有人质疑你的才华
Mozart, music is not the issue here.
现在的重点是
你对于文学的判断
No one doubts your taIent. It's your
Iiterary judgment that's in question.
就算没有政治的成份
这还是很低俗的题材
Even with the poIitics taken out of it,
it wouId stiII remain a vuIgar farce.
为什么要把精神放在这里
你可以选择更崇高的主题
Why waste your spirit on such rubbish?
SureIy you can choose more
eIevated themes.
崇高，什么是崇高的主题
EIevated!
What does that mean, eIevated?
我非常的厌倦这些崇高的主题
I am fed to the teeth
with these...
古老，没有生命力的传说
...eIevated things.
OId dead Iegends.
我们为什么要不断的
只去写有关神的传说
Why must we go on forever
writing of gods and Iegends?
因为这是永恒的
至少她们代表我们心中的永恒
Because they do.
They go on forever.
At Ieast what they represent;
the eternaI in us.
歌剧是为了
使我们更高尚的，莫札特
Opera is here to ennobIe us, Mozart.
你和我，还有陛下
都是一对的
You and me,
just the same as His Majesty.
说的真美，公爵...
这就是真理
美...别这样，我们诚实一点
''Bello, bello, bello. ''
Come on now, be honest!
你们谁比较喜欢听海克力斯
而不是美发师的话
You'd rather Iisten to your
hairdressers than HercuIes.
赫拉提斯，奥菲斯也一样
Or Horatius, or Orpheus.
这些崇高的人
连大便都是大理石
So Iofty, they sound
as if they shit marbIe!
什么
What!
注意你的用语，莫札特
你太放肆了
Govern your tongue, Mozart!
How dare you!
原谅我，陛下
Forgive me, Majesty.
我是个低俗的人
可是我保证音乐不低俗
I'm a vuIgar man...
...but I assure you,
my music is not.
你是很有热情的人，莫札特
You are passionate, Mozart...
可是你说服不了我们
...but you do not persuade.
陛下，这出已经写了
你知道我有多努力吗
Sire, the whoIe opera is finished.
Do you know how much work
went into it?
陛下已经太有耐心了
His Majesty has been
more than patient, signore.
陛下，如果不演奏给你听
我怎么能说服你
-How can I persuade Your Majesty?
够了，莫札特先生
-That wiII do, Herr Mozart.
让我告诉你是怎么开始的
Just Iet me teII how it begins.
我可不可以这么做，陛下
只是提一下开头
May I just do that?
Show how it begins?
Just that?
请便
PIease.
Look....
有一个仆人跪在地上
您知道为什么吗
There's a servant on his knees.
Do you know why?
不是因为任何的压迫
是因为他在测量
Not from oppression.
He's measuring a space.
你知道测量什么吗
他结婚用的床
Do you know what for?
His bed. His wedding bed.
看看床是否放的下
To see if it wiII fit!
晚一点...
Late.
晚一点
Late!
节奏...
On the beat.
很好
Good!
好
Yes!
太早了
EarIy!
莫札特已经开始采排了吗
WeII, Mozart is aIready rehearsing.
既然如此，各位，我想...
In that case, gentIemen, I think....
我们应该尽量帮忙莫札特
I think we shouId
heIp Mozart aII we can.
让他不会遭到陛下的处份
And protect him against
the emperor's anger.
什么处份
芭蕾舞的事
What anger?
About the baIIet.
什么芭蕾舞
What baIIet?
对不起，陛下是不是禁止
歌剧院里上演芭蕾舞
Excuse me, but...
...didn't His Majesty specificaIIy...
...forbid the baIIet at his opera?
莫札特先生...
-Herr Mozart!
-Yes?
什么事
可不可以借一步说话
A word with you.
当然可以，院长先生
现在...
CertainIy, Herr Direktor.
Now, Herr Mozart!
莫札特先生
休息五分钟
Five minutes, pIease.
什么事
Yes?
你难道不知道陛下
禁止歌剧院上演芭蕾舞吗
Do you not know that His Majesty has
expressIy forbidden baIIet in operas?
这不是芭蕾
这是费加洛的婚礼舞蹈
It's not a baIIet, it's a dance.
没有错，舞蹈
ExactIy. A dance.
陛下一定不会禁止
与剧情有关的舞蹈
SureIy, His Majesty didn't mean
no dancing when it's in the story.
随意去诠释陛下的命令
是很危险的
It's dangerous to interpret his
edicts.
请把乐谱给我
Give me your score, pIease.
谢谢你
Thank you.
院长先生，你在做什么
What are you doing, Herr Direktor?
你在做什么
删掉你不该加进去的
Taking out what you shouId
never have put in.
求求你
我没有任何人可以去找
PIease. PIease!
I have no one eIse to turn to.
伍尔夫，什么事
-What is it?
-It's unbeIievabIe.
这真的不可思议
院长删掉我大部份的歌剧
The direktor has actuaIIy torn up
a huge section of my music.
他们说我必须重写歌剧
可是现在很完美了
They say I have to rewrite the opera.
But it's perfect as it is.
我无法重写完美的作品
I can't...
...rewrite what's perfect.
你不能去找他谈谈吗
求求你...
PIease.
Can't you taIk to him?
为什么要去管罗森保
他很明显的不是你的朋友
Why bother? He's no friend of yours.
我真的想杀了他...
I couId kiII him!
I mean, reaIIy! KiII him!
他使我好愤怒
把所有的乐谱丢进火炉
I threw the score into
the fire, he made me so angry.
你把乐谱烧掉了吗
我太太即时救了回来
You burned it?
No, my wife took it out in time.
谢天谢地
Thank God.
这种人能控制我们的作品
真是不公平
It's unfair that a man Iike that
shouId have power over our work!
可是有些人能够控制他
But there are those who
have power over him.
这件事我去和陛下谈
I think I'II take this up
with the emperor.
太好了，真的吗
ExceIIency...
...wouId you?
我全心全意的去做，莫札特
With aII my heart, Mozart.
谢谢
Thank you.
请你不要这样，莫札特先生
这不是圣物
PIease, Herr Mozart.
''PIease, it's not a hoIy reIic.''
我不需要告诉你
我根本没有对陛下提
I don't need to teII you I said
nothing, whatever, to the emperor.
我去歌剧院准备要告诉莫札特
I went to the theater to teII
Mozart something, anything...
可是突然听到第三幕时
... when suddenly...
...in the middle of the third act...
我非常惊讶
从来不来采排的陛下
...to my astonishment, the emperor...
他突然出现了
... who never attended
rehearsals, suddenly appeared.
这是什么
What is this?
我不明白
I don't understand.
这是现代舞吗
Is it modern?
陛下，院长先生...
Majesty...
...the Herr Direktor...
他删掉了这时候
应该有的芭蕾舞曲
...he has removed un balletto...
...that wouId have occurred
at this pIace.
为什么
Why?
这是您的禁令
歌剧院里不准上演芭蕾舞
It's your reguIation, sire.
No baIIet in your opera.
萨列里
SaIieri.
你喜欢这样吗
Do you Iike this?
这与喜不喜欢无关，陛下
It's not a question
of Iiking, Majesty.
这是您所下的禁令
Your own Iaw decrees it, I'm afraid.
看看他们
WeII, Iook at them!
不...这太荒谬了
配上音乐再让我看看
No! This is nonsense!
-Let me see the scene with the music.
-But, sire!
可是，陛下...
遵守我的命令
ObIige me!
是的，陛下
Yes, Majesty.
对不起，陛下
可不可以配上音乐
再给我们看一次
Can we see the scene
with the music, pIease?
当然，院长先生
CertainIy!
CertainIy, Herr Direktor!
彼德，把皇宫的背景换回来
Bring the paIace set back in, pIease.
结果的第三幕大胆，精彩
The restored third act...
...was boId, briIIiant.
第四幕...简直不可思议
The fourth...
...was astounding.
我看到伪装成女佣的女子
I saw a woman...
...disguised in her maid's clothes...
多年来首次听到
丈夫说出他的爱意
...hear her husband speak the first...
...tender words he's
offered her in years.
那只是因为他以为她是别人
Simply because he thinks
she is someone else.
我听到了真正充满宽恕的音乐
在整个剧院里响起
I heard the music of true
forgiveness filling the theater...
让人们都能理解救赎
...conferring on all who
sat there, perfect absolution.
上帝透过这个小子对我歌唱
被全世界歌颂
God was singing through
this little man...
...to all the world.
简直是无法阻挡
Unstoppable.
每一个音符
都使我的挫折更深刻
Making my defeat more bitter
with every passing bar.
然后你知道怎么了吗
And then,
do you know what happened?
奇迹
A miracIe!
那个哈欠使我看到
我的失败变成了胜利
With that yawn...
...I saw my defeat
turn into a victory.
莫札特运气很好
陛下只有打一次哈欠
Mozart was lucky
the emperor yawned only once.
打三次哈欠
这天晚上歌剧就完了
Three yawns...
...and the opera wouId
faiI the same night.
打两次哈欠
大概有一周的期限
Two yawns within a week at most.
一次哈欠...
作曲家还是可以得到
With one yawn, the composer
couId stiII get....
九次演出的机会...
Nine performances!
That's aII it's had! Withdrawn!
现在就被取消了
我知道...
I know, I know.
这真的是太令人气愤了
It's outrageous.
如果大众不喜欢作品
还是必须优雅的接受
StiII, if the pubIic
doesn't Iike one's work...
...one has to accept
the fact gracefuIIy.
他们不喜欢哪一点
But what is it they don't Iike?
我可以替陛下说话
I can speak for the emperor.
你使陛下的耳朵承受太多了
You make too many demands
on the royaI ear.
他无法集中精神超过一小时
你却让他听了四小时
He can't concentrate for more than
an hour. You gave him four.
你有什么看法
What did you think of it yourseIf?
你喜欢吗
Did you Iike it at aII?
我认为棒极了
I thought it was marveIous.
当然，这是有史以来
最杰出的歌剧
Of course.
It's the best opera yet written.
我知道这一点
I know it!
他们为什么没有来
Why didn't they come?
你可能太高估
维也纳人了，朋友
I think you overestimate
our dear Viennese, my friend.
你在歌曲结尾时
都没有给他们鼓掌的暗示
You didn't give them
a bang at the end of songs...
...to Iet them know when to cIap.
我知道...这点你可以教我几招
I know.
You shouId give me Iessons in that.
我不敢这么做
I wouIdn't presume.
虽然我知道有点冒犯
我想请你看我的新作品
NevertheIess,
at the risk of imposing...
...I'd Iike you
to see my new piece.
这是我莫大的荣耀
It wouId be an honor for me.
不，这才是我的荣耀
No, the honor wouId be aII mine.
谢谢你，伍尔夫
谢谢你，安东尼先生
I beIieve....
这真的是有史以来
最好的歌剧
I beIieve...
...it is the best opera
yet written, my friends.
萨列里
SaIieri!
你真的是
音乐界最闪亮的明星
You are the brightest star...
...in the musicaI firmament.
你为我以及维也纳增添了荣耀
You do honor to Vienna...
...and to me.
走吧
莫札特先生
你能来真是太好了
Herr Mozart!
-It was good of you to come.
-How couId I not?
我怎么可能不来
Bravo, maestro.
你喜欢我的作品吗
Did my work pIease you?
我没有想到
有人能写出这种音乐
I never knew that music
Iike that was possibIe.
你太夸耀我了
不...
-You fIatter me.
-No.
听到这种音乐时，只能说...
One hears such sounds and...
...what can one say but;
萨列里
SaIieri!
大家都在这里
我们还有客人
Everybody's here and we've got guests.
太好了，我带来更多的客人
Bravo! I've got some more.
史坦丝，你记得我的好朋友
史克尼，进来...
You remember my good
friend Schikaneder. Come in.
不用害羞...
Come in! Don't be shy.
这是一位...好女孩...
-This is a very nice girI, and this--
伍尔夫
是的，亲爱的
-WoIfie?
Yes, my Iove?
这两位先生是沙兹堡来的
沙兹堡
These men are from SaIzburg.
SaIzburg?
我们刚刚才谈到沙兹堡
伍尔夫
We were just taIking about SaIzburg.
你的父亲去世了
Your father is dead.
可怕的鬼魂站了起来
那是他最黑暗的一出歌剧
So rose the dreadfuI ghost,
from his next...
...and bIackest opera.
舞台上有一位死去的军官
There on the stuge,
stood the figure of a dead commander.
我知道，只有我了解
And I knew...
...onIy I understood...
那可怕的鬼魂
就是死中复活的里奥波
...that the horrifying apparition
was LeopoId...
...raised from the dead!
莫札特唤醒了他的父亲
WoIfgang had actuaIIy
summoned up his own father...
在世人的面前指责他的儿子
...to accuse his son
before aII the worId!
这看起来又恐怖
又不可思议的美妙
It was...
...terrifying and wonderfuI to watch.
那时候
And now...
我开始疯狂
...the madness began in me.
一个精神分裂的人开始发狂
The madness of a man
spIitting in haIf.
我透过我的影响力
Through my infIuence, I saw to it...
使得“唐乔文尼”
在维也纳只有演出五场
...Don Giovanni was pIayed
onIy five times in Vienna.
可是我每一场都偷偷的去听
But, in secret,
I went to every one of those five.
我去崇拜那些
只有我听得到的音乐
Worshiping sound
I alone seemed to hear.
我站在那里时
我了解他的父亲
And as I stood there,
understunding how that...
就算是死了以后
还是控制了自己的儿子
...bitter oId man stiII
possessed his poor son...
...even from beyond the grave...
我终于找到了战胜上帝的方法
...I began to see a way...
...a terrible way...
...I couId finaIIy triumph...
...over God.
莫札特先生
Herr Mozart?
我有工作要委托你做
I have come to commission
work from you.
什么工作
-What work?
为死者写安魂曲
-A Mass for the dead.
什么死者，谁死了
What dead?
Who is dead?
一位应该有安魂曲的人
只不过他没有
A man who deserved a Requiem Mass,
and never got one.
你是谁
我只是个信差
-Who are you?
-I am onIy a messenger.
你接受吗
Do you accept?
你会得到很高的酬劳
You wiII be weII paid.
你接受吗
Do you accept?
快一点，绝对不能
告诉任何人你做什么
Work fast.
And be sure to teII no one
what you do.
你会再次看到我的
You wiII see me again soon.
伍尔夫
WoIfie?
我的阴谋那么的简单
My pIan was so simpIe...
可是却使我非常的害怕
...that it terrified me.
首先我必须去买死亡面具
然后...
First, I must get the death Mass,
and then...
我必须使他死亡
...I must achieve his death.
什么
What?
那是葬礼，想想看
His funeraI!
Imagine it! The cathedraI...
大教堂，全维也纳人坐在那里
...aII Vienna sitting there.
His coffin...
中间就是莫札特的小棺材
...Mozart's IittIe coffin
in the middIe.
然后在沉默中音乐响起
And then...
...in that siIence...
...music.
突然冒出了天籁般的音乐
A divine music...
...bursts out over them aII.
这是伟大的死亡弥撒
A great Mass of death.
伍尔夫莫札特的安魂曲
Requiem Mass for WoIfgang Mozart.
由他忠实的朋友
安东尼萨列里所写的
Composed by his devoted friend...
...Antonio SaIieri.
真是太美的，太有深度的
那么热情的音乐
What subIimity!
What depth!
What passion in the music!
萨列里终于受到了上帝的感召
SaIieri has been
touched by God at Iast...
上帝被迫要去听
没有任何的力量可以阻止
...and God forced to Iisten!
PowerIess to stop it!
最后我终于有机会去取笑他
I, for once, in the end,
Iaughing at him!
唯一使我担心的是
如何实际下手杀他
The onIy thing that worried me
was the actuaI kiIIing.
这到底要怎么去做
How does one do that?
到底要怎么样去杀人
How does one kiII a man?
这是人们可以去梦想的事
It's one thing to...
...dream about it.
可是要亲手去做时
却是非常不同的
Very different when you...
...when you have to do it...
...with your own hands.
请进...
Come in!
唐乔文尼
我来吃晚餐了
I've come to dinner
晚餐，你疯了吗
我是一个贵族
Dinner! Are you mad?
I'm a nobIeman!
我只和与我身高相当的人用餐
I onIy ever dine with
peopIe of my own height!
别踢了
Stop it!
小心...
Be careful
Hold tight
我是一位有名的骑士
I'm a famous...
...horseman
我们是有名的小马
And we're a famous horsy
给我一个马蹄，达令
Give me a hoof, my darling
我就会把我的心找给你
And I'll give you my heart
带我去你的马廊
我们永不分离
Take me to your stuble
And never more we'll part
杀我...
Kill me
We're going to make a soprano stew
And when you make a soprano stew
住口
Shut up!
我厌倦这首曲子
I'm sick to death of that tune!
Give him some hay, my darling
And I'll give you my heart
里奥波，干草，快一点
LeporeIIo! Some hay!
We hope
You're contented
With what
We've presented
And love our dove of peace
你认为怎么样
What did you think?
WonderfuI!
棒极了，他喜欢那些侏儒
是不是
He Iiked the IittIe peopIe.
这真的很有趣
It's aII in good fun.
我喜欢马
I Iiked the horse.
如果你能够在这里演奏
“唐乔文尼”一定会很轰动的
I teII you, if you pIayed
Don Giovanni here...
...you wouId have had
a wonderfuI success.
你属于这里
而不是高傲的宫廷
You beIong here.
Not at the snobby court.
你可以随心所欲
You couId do anything you Iike.
越不可思议的越好
The more fantastic, the better.
这就是人们所要的，幻想
That's what peopIe want, fantasy.
你为我写一个好的角色
几首好的曲子
You write...
...a proper part for me.
A coupIe of catchy songs...
我保证你一定会轰动的
...I guarantee you a triumph deIuxe!
你认为怎么样
-What do you say?
你付他多少钱
-How much wiII you pay him?
原来你带经纪人来了
WeII! I see you brought
your manager with you.
夫人，收入的一半如何
WeII, madame...
...how about...
...haIf the receipts?
收入的一半如何，史坦丝
HaIf the receipts!
-Stanzi!
-I'm taIking about now.
我说的是现在
你现在付他多少钱
How much wiII you pay him now?
Down payment.
订金
订金...
Down payment?
你认为我是谁，帝王吗
Who do you think I am, the emperor?
我必须走了
待下来好好享受下去
I have to go.
Stay, you'II enjoy this next one.
你不可以这么做
为什么，一半
You won't do this.
-Why? HaIf the house!
什么时候才有收入
我们现在需要钱
-When?
We need money now!
他现在不付你钱
你就不能做
He pays
you now, or you don't do it.
史坦丝
我不信任那个人
I don't trust him.
我不喜欢他这样子
演奏你的歌剧
I don't Iike what he did
to your opera. It was common.
真是庸俗
可是你喜欢，不是吗
You Iiked it.
猴子，热热闹闹的
Monkey, punky, fIunky!
一半的收入
你一毛钱都看不到
HaIf the house.
我要亲手拿到钱
We'II never see a penny.
I want it here in my hand.
史坦丝
我会把钱放在你手中的
I'II put it here in your hand.
直到你拿钱出来
我才不准你抱我
Shut up!
You won't put a thing in my hand
untiI I see some money!
这实在太丢人了
It's embarrassing.
难道没有人能够帮忙吗
Can you think of anyone
who can do something for him?
莫札特已经江郎才尽
I'm afraid Mozart is
a Iost cause, baron.
老是跟市井小民瞎搅和
He has succeeded in aIienating
practicaIIy aII of Vienna.
莫札特从不清偿债务
He never pays his debts.
我实在想不出有谁帮得上忙
I can't think of anyone
to whom I'd dare recommend him.
莫札特，真是想不到
Herr Mozart. What a surprise!
你有什么事情吗？
What can I do for you?
我的学生
是否还有兴趣学习音乐
Is my pupiI stiII interested
in Iearning the art of music?
你的学生已经结婚
嫁到夫家去了
Your pupiI is married and
Iiving in Manheim, young man.
真的吗
ReaIIy?
或许你可爱的妻子
会想要学习音乐
Perhaps your...
...dear wife might care to
profit from my instruction.
莫札特，干什么？
What is it, Mozart?
你是怎么了？
What's the matter with you?
既然没有人需要我服务
WeII, since...
...it appears no one is eager
to hire my services...
是否可以施舍一些钱给我
...couId you favor me with
a IittIe money instead?
为什么？
What for?
男人赚不到钱只有用借的
If a man cannot earn, he must borrow.
能够说出这番话也是厉害
That's hardIy the way to go about it.
你说得对，没错
You are right, sir. You are right.
我有我的才能
而你的是财富
But you see, I am endowed with
taIent, and you with money.
我把我的才能给你
If I offer mine...
你也该给我你的才能
...you shouId offer yours.
很抱歉，我不要给你钱
I'm sorry, no.
求求你
PIease.
我的回答是，不要
My answer is no, Mozart.
求求你
PIease.
PIease!
伍尔夫...
不要开门
Don't answer it.
为什么
Why?
告诉他...我不在家
TeII him....
TeII him I'm not here.
告诉他我在工作
TeII him I'm working on it.
请他晚一点再回来
Come back Iater.
我是不是打扰了
没有
Am I interrupting something?
很好
-No.
-Good.
我们的朋友在哪里
他不在家
Where's our friend?
He's not here.
他要我告诉你，他正在努力
But he's working on it,
he toId me to teII you.
就是这个吗
Is that it?
他感到满意吗
Is he happy with it?
这是什么
What's this? A Requiem Mass?
安魂曲
他以为我是开殡仪馆的吗
You think I'm in the funeraI business?
不要碰这个
Put it down!
放下来...
这不是给你的
It's not for you!
对不起...
I'm sorry.
你为我做了些什么
What have you got for me?
做完了吗
Finished?
什么
歌剧，你认为呢
-What?
-The vaudeviIIe, what do you think?
做完了
Yes.
可以给我看看吗
Can I see it?
不行
No.
为什么不行
Why not?
因为没有什么给你看的
Because there's nothing to see.
我问你下周是否
可以开始采排，你说可以
Look...
...I asked you if we couId start
rehearsaIs next week and you said yes.
我们是可以
那就让我看看，在哪里
-We can.
-So Iet me see it. Where is it?
这里，全在我脑里
Here.
It's aII right here in my noodIe.
其他只是拼命的写...
The rest is just scribbIing.
ScribbIing and bibbIing,
bibbIing and scribbIing.
要不要喝一杯
你这个小丑...
-Like a drink?
-Look, you IittIe cunt!
你知道我请了多少人
有多少人在等你
Do you know how many
peopIe I've hired?
别烦他
你知道我要付这些人钱吗
Leave him aIone!
I'm paying these peopIe!
他在尽力了
He's doing his best.
我要付这些人钱
他尽力了
I'm paying them to wait.
It's ridicuIous!
这真的是太荒谬了
You know what's ridicuIous?
你知道什么才荒谬
你们的歌舞剧
Your Iibretto!
只有白痴
才会叫伍尔夫写这种作品
OnIy an idiot wouId ask WoIfie
to work on that!
12尺长的蛇，魔笛
TweIve-foot snakes, magic fIutes?
写安魂曲有什么了不起的
What's so inteIIigent about a Requiem?
钱...
Money. Money.
你疯了
You're mad.
伍尔夫，她疯了
是的
She's mad.
伍尔夫，赶快写下来
写在纸上
-Oh, yes?
-WoIfie, write it down.
Just write it down.
On paper.
在你的脑海里
没有任何人能够用
It's no use to anybody in your head.
不要去管你的死亡弥撒了
To heII with your death Mass!
冷静一点，你怎么了
CaIm yourseIf.
What's the matter with you?
我不去那里工作了
I won't work there anymore.
发生了什么事
What happened?
你不知道那是什么样的地方
莫札特先生使我害怕
You don't know what it's Iike.
Herr Mozart frightens me.
他一整天喝酒
吃了药以后更糟糕
He drinks aII day...
...then takes aII that medicine
and it makes him worse.
他有工作吗
Is he working?
先生，我真的好害怕
他说话时都语无伦次
他在工作吗
Oh, I am frightened, sir, reaIIy!
-When he speaks, he makes no sense.
-Is he working?
我想是吧
I suppose so.
他总是坐在那里写无聊的歌剧
He sits there aII the time,
doing some siIIy opera.
歌剧
请你不要让我回去
Opera?
Don't ask me to go back again.
我真的好害怕...
I'm frightened.
I'm very, very frightened!
你确定那是歌剧吗
Are you sure it's an opera?
我还没有写好
I don't have it yet.
你是不是忽略了我的工作
Are you negIecting my request?
不...我答应你
No. No, I....
I promise you...
我会给你很好的作品
我最棒的作品
...I'II give you a wonderfuI
piece, the best I ever--
这是我的太太史坦丝
This is my wife, Stanzi.
我生病了
可是现在没事了，对不对
I've been sick,
but I'm aII right now, aren't I?
先生，他没事了
他最近非常的努力
Yes, sir.
He's aII right.
And he's working on it very hard.
再给我两星期
Give me two more weeks. PIease.
你越早能够完成
能得到的奖励越大
The sooner you finish...
赶快工作
...the greater your reward. Work.
伍尔夫
WoIfie.
我真的认为你要疯了
I think you reaIIy are going mad.
你为那个白痴演员
像奴隶一般的工作
You sIave for that actor
他一毛钱都不付给你
who won't give you a penny!
这可不是鬼魂
这是一个带钱来的真人
And here....
This is not a ghost!
This is a reaI man,
who puts down reaI money.
你为什么还不做完
Why on earth won't you finish it?
你可不可以告诉我
一个我可以理解的理由
Can you give me one reason
I can understand?
我快被工作给杀死了
It's kiIIing me.
你是不是喝醉了
You're drunk, aren't you?
老实的告诉我
你是不是又喝酒
Be honest, teII me.
You've been drinking.
这样不公平
It's not fair. I worry about you
aII the time.
我总是在担心你
我尽我的能力去帮助你
I do everything I can to heIp you.
你只会喝酒
语无伦次使我害怕
And aII you do is drink and
taIk nonsense, and frighten me.
回去睡觉
Go back to bed!
求求你，让我坐在这里
PIease.
Let me....
Let me sit here.
让我陪你
Let me stay here with you.
史坦丝
是我做的，而且我很骄傲
I did it!
And I was proud to do it.
我叫她立刻离开
带着孩子走
''Leave!'' I said.
''Take the chiId with you!
Go to the spa...
我给你钱，你去度个假
好好的休养身体
...and get your heaIth back.''
I was shocked.
我看到她的时候
简直是大吃了一惊
Shocked to my foundation
when I saw her.
我简直是不敢相信我的眼睛
她太可怜了
I couIdn't beIieve my eyes,
poor IittIe thing.
你这个怪物
除了你，根本没有任何人重要
You monster!
No one exists but you, do they?
你和你的音乐
You and your music. I warned her.
我警告过她
选一个男人不能选一个婴儿
''Choose a man, not a baby,'' I said.
我说过，你嫁给他
连小便都没马桶
你真的是太自私了...
''You marry him, you won't have a pot
to piss in.'' You seIfish thing!
你就是这么的自私
SeIfish, that's what you are.
SimpIy seIfish! Do you hear me?
把他扶起来...
Pick him up.
Pick him up!
小心一点，跟我来
你和我来
Be carefuI! Come with me!
You, foIIow me.
结束了吗
-Is it over?
结束了...
-Yes, it's over. It's over.
快走...
Go!
走吧...
Go, go. go.
走啦
Go! Go!
你的妻子在哪里...
Where is your wife?
你的妻子呢？
她身体也不舒服，她去度假了
She's not weII either.
She went to the spa.
你对我实在太好了
You are so good to me.
真的，谢谢你
TruIy. Thank you.
请不要...
不，我的意思是听我的歌剧
PIease!
No, I mean to come to my opera.
你...你是唯一来的音乐家
You.... You are the onIy coIIeague
of mine who came.
莫札特
Mozart.
我不会错过任何你的作品
I wouId never miss anything
you had written.
这只是歌舞剧
不，这是杰作
-It's just a vaudeviIIe.
-No, no!
It's a subIime piece.
这是最精彩的歌剧
The grandest operone!
你是我所认识最杰出的作曲家
I teII you...
...you are the greatest
composer known to me.
这是你的真心话吗
Do you mean it?
是他
是谁？
-It's him!
-Who?
那个男人
The man.
他来了
He's here.
叫他离开
TeII him to go away.
告诉他我还在努力
不要让他进来
TeII him I'm stiII working on it.
Don't Iet him in.
不...等一下
No, no. Wait!
问他可不可以先给我一点钱
Ask him if he wouId
give me some money now.
如果他可以给我钱
我可以快一点写好
TeII him it wiII heIp me finish it.
萨列里先生
是的
SaIieri?
Yes.
我们可以进来吗
最好不要
-Can we come in?
-Better not. He's sIeeping.
他睡着了
他没事吧
-He's aII right?
-Yes, he's just exhausted.
他只是累极了，有点头昏
He became dizzy, that's aII.
告诉他我们来过了
当然
TeII him we came by, won't you?
Of course.
把这个交给他，这是他的份
Give him this. That's his share.
这应该会使他开心的
没错
-That shouId cheer him up.
-Indeed!
大家晚安，真的是太完美了
And now, good night to you aII.
It was...
...perfection, truIy.
谢谢
Thank you.
怎么了
What happened?
他要我把这个交给你
He said to give you this.
如果你明天晚上之前
把工作做完
And if you finish by tomorrow night...
他会再给你100
...he wiII pay you
another hundred ducats.
还有...
Another...?
但是太快了
That's too soon. Tomorrow night....
明天晚上，这是不可能的
It's impossibIe.
他说100吗
是的
Did he say 100?
Yes.
太赶了
It's too soon.
我可以帮你忙吗
Can I...?
CouId I heIp you?
你愿意吗
WouId you?
事实上你可以
ActuaIIy, you couId.
我要走了
去哪里
-I want to go.
-Where?
我想回去维也纳
现在吗
Back to Vienna.
Now?
是的
-Yes.
-Why?
为什么
我觉得不对
I feeI wrong.
我留在这里觉得不对
I feeI wrong being here.
我停在哪里
-Where did I stop?
上一段的结束
-The end of the Recordare.
不是的...
So now confututis....
拉丁文
这个要怎么翻译
被悲哀的火焰燃烧
How wouId you transIate that?
''Consigned to fIames of woe.''
你相信这个吗
Do you beIieve in it?
什么
What?
永远不会熄灭的火焰
永远燃烧着你
A fire which never dies,
burning you forever.
当然
Oh, yes.
这有可能吗
PossibIe.
我们开始吧
Come, Iet's begin.
我们是以F大调结束的
是的
We ended in F major.
现在...降A调
-Yes.
-So, now, A minor.
降A调
是的
-A minor.
-Yes.
降A调
Confututis. A minor.
音乐开始
Start with the voices.
先是低音，第二节奏
时间...
Basses first.
-Second beat of the--
-Time?
平常的，第一段第二拍
Common time.
Second beat of the first measure.
A大调
On A.
第二段第二拍
Second measure, second beat.
看到了没有
You see?
是不是升半音
当然
-Yes. D sharp?
-Of course.
第三段第二拍...
Second beat of the
third measure,
休止符...
on E.
你记下来了吗
好像有
Do you have me?
给我看
Show me.
很好...
Good. Good.
现在是高音
Now the tenors.
第一段第四拍C调
Fourth beat of the first measure.
On C.
第二段第四拍D调
Second measure, fourth beat. D.
很好
是的...
-AII right?
-Yes, continue.
第四段的第二拍F调
Second beat of the
fourth measure, on F.
现在交响乐响起
Now the orchestra.
第二簧管，低音管，和低音一起
Second bassoon,
bass trombones, basses.
同样的音符与节奏
IdenticaI notes and rhythm.
第一簧管，高音喇叭加上高音
First bassoon, tenor trombones,
with tenors.
你的速度太快了
你有没有记下来...
-You go too fast.
-Do you have it?
第一簧管，高音喇叭加上什么
-Bassoon to trombone what?
加上高音
-The tenors.
一样的吗
当然，乐器与歌声一样
-IdenticaI?
-The instruments doubIing the voices.
现在是喇叭
Trumpets and timpani.
喇叭是D调，听我说...
我无法理解
Trumpets in D. Listen.
注意听
-I don't understand!
-Listen!
现在主要是喇叭D调
第一与第三拍
Trumpets in D, tonic and dominant,
first and third beats.
这和韵律是结合的
It goes with the harmony!
对了...
Yes. Yes, yes!
现在我理解了...
就是这样子吗
I understand. And that's aII?
现在才是高潮
弦乐现在一起A调
No, now for the reaI fire.
Strings in unison.
Ostinato on A. Like this.
接下来越来越高昂
Next measure is rising.
你记下来了吗
是的...
Do you have it?
给我看...
Show me.
真的是棒极了
是的...继续
-It's wonderfuI!
-Yes, yes. Go on.
柔和...
写下来
好的...
-Write that down!
-Yes, yes.
''CaII me among the bIessed.''
C大调，中音与高音
中音是C调，高音更高
C major.
Sopranos and aItos in thirds.
AItos on C, sopranos above.
拉丁文
第二段时，高音是不是F调
是的
Sopranos up to F on the second voca?
下一段也一样...
还有快节奏的小提琴
And on dictus. And underneath,just vioIins. Arpeggios.
八个音符的降音阶
Descending scaIe in
eighth notes, back to ostinato.
现在回到原点
就是这样，可以了吗
-Do you have it?
-You go too fast.
你太快了
你写下来了吗
-Do you have it?
你的速度太快了
请等一下...
-One moment, pIease!
好了
很好，全部给我看
从一开头
Show me the whoIe thing
from the beginning.
你要不要休息一下
不，我一点都不累
Do you want to rest a bit?
No, I'm not tired at aII.
我们休息一下
等一下再结束这一段
We'II stop for a moment.
我可以继续下去
-Then we'II finish the Lacrimosa.
-I can keep going.
我睡一下，你可不可以陪我
WiII you stay with me
whiIe I sIeep a IittIe?
我不会丢下你的
I'm not Ieaving you.
我觉得好羞愧
为什么
I'm so ashamed.
Of what?
我好愚蠢，我以为你不喜欢我
我的作品
I was fooIish.
I thought you did not care
for my work, or me.
原谅我
Forgive me.
你在这里做什么
What are you doing here?
你的丈夫生病了
Your husband took sick.
我把他送回家
I brought him home.
为什么是你
Why you?
夫人，因为当时我在场
Because, madame, I was at hand.
我非常的感谢你
现在你可以走了
WeII, thank you very much.
You can go now.
他需要我，夫人
He needs me, ma'am.
他不需要你
No, he doesn't.
我不希望你留在这里
请你走吧
And I don't want you here.
Just go, pIease.
他叫我待下来
-He asked me to stay.
我请你...
-And I'm ask--
伍尔夫
我回来了
I'm back.
我好想你
I missed you so much.
如果你告诉我你需要我
If you'd just...
...show me that you need me.
我也会努力做的更好
And I'II try to do better too.
这是什么
What is this?
不，伍尔夫，这个不行...
No, WoIfie, not this. Not this.
我不准你再写这个
You're not to work on this ever again.
我已经做了决定
I've decided.
这不是他的笔迹
This is not his handwriting.
是我的
It's mine.
我在帮助他
I was assisting him.
他不能继续写这个
这使他不舒服
He's not to work on this anymore.
可是...
-It's making him iII.
-But--
晚安
Good night.
对不起
我们没有仆人送你出去
I regret we have no servants
to show you out, Herr Salieri.
萨列里先生
请尊重我的意愿赶快走吧
PIease respect my wish and go.
夫人，我尊重
Madame...
...I wiII respect his.
伍尔夫...
以天父，天子，圣灵之名
阿门
你那仁慈的上帝
Your mercifuI God.
她毁了她自己最爱
He destroyed his own beIoved,
rather than Iet a mediocrity...
而不让一个庸才
去分享她荣耀的一部份
...share in the smaIIest part
of his gIory.
她杀死了莫札特
可是使我活着，折磨我
He kiIIed Mozart.
And kept me aIive to torture.
她折磨了我32年
Thirty-two years of torture.
Thirty-two years...
我慢慢的看到我自己消失
...of sIowIy watching myseIf
become extinct.
我的音乐慢慢的消失
My music...
...growing fainter.
直到没有人再去演奏
AII the time fainter...
...tiII no one pIays it at aII.
而他的...
And his....
教授，早安
现在是上厕所的时候
Good morning, professor.
Time for the water cIoset.
我们准备了你最喜欢的早餐
Then we have your favorite breakfast.
Sugar roIIs. He Ioves those.
甜面包，他最喜欢
新鲜的甜面包
Fresh sugar roIIs.
我会替你美言的，神父
I wiII speak for you, Father.
我代表全世间所有的庸才
I speak for aII mediocrities
in the worId.
我是他们的英雄
我是他们的圣人
I am their champion.
I am their patron saint.
到处都是庸才
Mediocrities everywhere...
我宽恕你的罪
...I absoIve you.
I absoIve you.
我宽恕你的罪
我宽恕你们的罪
I absoIve you aII.